<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks upon a scurrilous libel called An argrument, shewing that a standing army is inconsistent with a free government, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58503</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13415137</idno>
  <idno type="VID">99474</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240909333</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R667</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13415137</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 474:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks upon a scurrilous libel called An argrument, shewing that a standing army is inconsistent with a free government, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A criticism of John Trenchard's An argument shewing, that a standing army is inconsistent with a free government.  1697.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Trenchard, John, 1662-1723. --  Argument shewing that a standing army is inconsistent with a free government.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Standing army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99474:1"/>
            <p>REMARKS UPON A <hi>Scurrilous Libel;</hi> CALLED <hi>An Argument, shewing that a</hi> Standing Army <hi>is inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stent with a</hi> Free Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the YEAR 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99474:2"/>
            <head>DEDICATION TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Itch of Popularity is an Epidemical Disease, and Men often are tickled with Fame of any kind, though purchac'd like that of <hi>Erostratus, viz.</hi> by throwing the <hi>Firebrand.</hi> Much such another Glory must the Author of this Pamphlet set up for. But to encourage so hardy an Undertaking, 'tis well he tells us, <hi>That the King is a Prince in whom we know no Vices, but what have been esteem'd Vertues in others,</hi> viz. <hi>his undeserved Clemency to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> 'Tis a Sign indeed that he believes him merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, even to a Fault; otherwise this licentious Piece of Scrible would never have dared to expose its Face in the World, for fear of exposing that of the Author's a little indecently, and well if he scaped so. However, if Mercy be the King's Fault, 'tis none of this Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer's; for never was Crown'd Head treated more bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barously
<pb facs="tcp:99474:3"/>by a Mass of the rankest Suggestions that ever past with Impunity.</p>
            <p>'Tis true if he meant what he says, that the Royal Clemency was his only Vice, the Author's whole Outcry of Slavery would be husht, and his Argument vain. But this Author that never says one thing twice, can write Panegyricks in one Page, and Satyrs in another; and begs your leave that Prevarication, Inconsistence, <hi>Chimera</hi>'s, and even Contradiction it self, may be currant Standard in his way of VVriting; otherwise the greatest Beauties of his whole Argument will be lost.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99474:3"/>
            <head>REMARKS UPON THE Argument, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THis Author, by his Zeal, and the Choice of his Subject, sets up for no less than a Patriot, and possibly may be some small <hi>Murmurer</hi> that he is not a Statesman; for his deep penetration into Publick Dangers, and his High Wisdom in projecting the Politicks to avert them, undoubtedly make him fancy that he deserves the Honour of a Post of Trust</p>
            <p>And truly now I have call'd him Murmurer, methinks his whole Pamphlet speaks as much: and truly as he has discover'd such Manacles and Shackles, and Iron Rods hanging over the whole poor Nation, 'tis a shrewd sign his Genius inclines to the <hi>Melancholy;</hi> for none see Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions like the <hi>Hypocondriack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Fit of Enthusiasm he sets Pen to Paper; and pointing us to a Court-corner, he shews us a terrible Goblin call'd <hi>Slavery</hi> just peeping from behind the Hangings.</p>
            <p>This impending Danger is, belike, no less than shakin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the whole Fabrick of the English Government, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99474:4"/>us know from what Hands; and on what weak side the Blow shall be given, he begins with a learned Description of the English Monarchy, tells us, <hi>That our Constitution depends upon a due Balance between King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and that Balance depends upon the mutual Occasions and Necessities they have of one another; if this Cement be once broke, there is an actual Dissolution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now this Balance can never be preserved, but by an Union of the Natural and Artificial Strength of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; that is, by making the Militia to consist of the same Persons as have the Property; or otherwise the Government is violent, and against Nature, and cannot possibly continue, but the Constitution must break the Army (viz.</hi> a standing one,) <hi>or the Army will destroy the Constitution. For it is universally true, that where-ever the Militia is, there is, or will be the Government in a short time,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But where the Militia consists of the same Parts as the Government, where the King as General, the Lords by virtue of their Castles and Honours, the Great Commanders, and the Freeholders by their Tenures the Body of the Army; so 'tis next to impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for an Army thus constituted, to act to the Disadvantage of the Constitution, unless we con'd suppose them Felons</hi> de se, &amp;c. <hi>And no Nation ever preserv'd its Liberty, that maintain'd in Army otherwise constituted within the Seat of their Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this he proceeds to tell us over and over, that a standing Army of <hi>Mercenaries,</hi> none excepted, as having no Right in the <hi>Property,</hi> and consequently no ways in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terested in the Publick Safety, if kept up in Time of Peace, must undoubtedly enslave the Kingdom, and end in nothing less than the inevitable Ruine of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</p>
            <p>This Assertion he endeavours to prove by several Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, and some Domestick Instances.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99474:4"/>
            <p> Here our Argumentator founds the whole stress and merit of his Cause; <hi>viz.</hi> in the Trust and Fidelity of a Country <hi>Militia</hi> above that of a standing Army, and consequently the whole National Safety secured in their Hands, as being the <hi>Freeholders, Masters of the Property,</hi> such as have <hi>Foci</hi> as well as <hi>Arae</hi> to fight for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This indeed is an admirable and safe composition of an Army: But where is it to be found! For supposing the Militia of the Kingdom rais'd for Service, possibly, to oppose an Invasion at home, or follow their Royal Master, their Leader and General, to subject or reduce a Revolt in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. supposing this Army Sixty, (as our Author advises) or Six score thousand, how many Freeholders would he find amongst them. 'Tis true upon a fair peaceable Summer's Day, or a Lord Mayor's Shew, we shall have Buff Coats and Silver Head-pieces, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial Cits, House-keepers, and who not; nay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a whole prancing Royal Regiment of all Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pound Men: But how far will they march? To <hi>Islington</hi> Common, or the Artillery-Ground?</p>
            <p>How many of the substantial Property-men of the Nation upon the Irruption of real Danger, does he sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose will leave their dear Wives, their Families, their Children, their Trades, and their safe Nests, and soft Beds at home, to face Death and Danger abroad; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when their very Constitution allows a <hi>Militia</hi> man the Liberty of sending a Hireling in his stead.</p>
            <p>But if this Author, to compose his Militia of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, would desire a Law made to oblige the Master of the Family to march in his own proper Person; the very Imposition of such a Law would be deem'd a greater <hi>English</hi> Slavery, than the very worst and heaviest Shack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les our Scribler pretends to fear: Such an Imposition of the King's Service (for so I'll call it) would be thought
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99474:5"/>a greater Vassalage than the Old Knight-Service, and all the ancient Villanage of <hi>England.</hi> So that on the other side, if the Freehold Militia are, and must be free still to depute, what then will compose such an Army for Service, but Varlets and Mercinaries, glean'd from the Plough and the Cart, the Labourer, the Porter, the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, and what not; so that this so magnified Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, this illustrious, distinguishing characteristick, and particular Mark of Honour betwixt a Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and a Militia utterly vanishes, and so our Author's strongest Pillar falls to the Ground; whilst the main Body of the Standing Army, or the Train'd-Band one, will at last bear both equal weight in that Scale; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently (to use his own Words) have <hi>one as little tye to engage their Fidelity, as the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis true our Argumentator seems to set some distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon one Hireling and t'other; <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinary</hi> in the Militia is as good as a Property-Man, and will be true to his Country's Interest, in <hi>respect to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster that pays him and sends him forth:</hi> A very feeble Bond of Fidelity, if that Dependance be all the Tye. For I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fancy what wonderful Ascendant a private Man can have over a temporary Hireling Soldier, when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Pay and Bread from Crown'd Heads is no Security in that Case. No, 'tis as Inclination leads, and the Cause pleases, that give Edge to the Sword, and Vigour and Faith to the Arm that wields it.</p>
            <p>However our Argumentator takes it for granted, that Inconstancy, Levity, Infidelity, and indeed every dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Vice, every Insult of Arbitrary Oppression and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and all the Natural Tendencies to an Universal Slavery, run in the very Veins of a Standing Army, when all the shining Vertues imaginable are the unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion'd Graces of a Militia: and accordingly tells us,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99474:5"/>Page 14. <hi>If the late King</hi> James <hi>wou'd have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with Arbitrary Power, without bringing in Popery, he and his Black Guards</hi> (meaning that Standing Army) <hi>would have bound us hand and foot before this time. But when their ill contriv'd Oppression came home to their own doors, they quickly shew'd the World how different a thing it was to suffer themselves, and to make other People suffer; and so we came by our Deliverance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This, at first sight, looks like a plausible Tale on this Scribler's side, for facilitating the dangerous Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Slavery into <hi>England,</hi> the grand Argument he drives at. But here I would ask the Author, his whole Party, nay, and the whole World, how in the present State of <hi>England,</hi> 'tis consonant either with Reason or Sence, so much as to suppose any such thing as an <hi>English</hi> Slavery under a Monarchical Administration, or the least Royal Temptation even to incline that way, from any Motive whatsoever but Popery. For I would desire any reasonable Man to give me even one Shadow of a sensible National Danger of that kind from any Protestant Crown'd Head whatever, that does, or shall inherit the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For in the first place, what Jemm does the present, though limited, (as we call it) Royalty of the <hi>English</hi> Diadem want, to satisfie even the ultimate Ambition of the Crown'd Head that wears it, except the gratifying of a dissatisfy'd contrary Zealot, that dares venture, and that only upon the Impulse of a bigotted Faith, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding his Crown below, by a stretch of our Liberty, the <hi>English</hi> Rights and Laws, and all, for the imaginary gaining of a sairer Crown above. And here pray let us look back to the Arbitrary Power that King <hi>James,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, <hi>was not contented with,</hi> and see if he made so much as one step or movement that way, that was so much as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99474:6"/>the least Arbitrary but purely for Popery-sake. Did he set up an Ecclesiastick-Court that carried a Pretence of Protestant Church-Government, but for the <hi>Roman</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? Did he indulge and caress the Dissenters for any thing but self-sake; <hi>viz.</hi> that one Indulgence might make way for another, the Conventicle usher in the Mass-House! Did he turn out the Mourning Gowns at <hi>Maud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> for any thing but the Introduction of his own Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the Triumphant Hoods and Cowles there! Or did he make the least stretch of Right, or Dispensation of Law, or <hi>Quo Warranto</hi>'s, or Modell'd Charters, for any Earthly Cause, but as an Attack, Trench, and Mine against those dreadful Protestant Bulwarks the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Test,</hi> &amp;c. and all in pure Favour still to his Darling Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists under their lamented legal Exclusion from Pow'r and Trust! Nay, how many thousand now in <hi>England,</hi> believe that his private <hi>French</hi> League, that made such a noise in the World, was of no less Import than inviting over a Popish <hi>French</hi> Pow'r, in case of too weak an <hi>English</hi> one at home, for the great Work, as <hi>Coleman</hi> tells you, of rooting out the Northern Heresie, though to no less hazard than even the shaking of his Diadem; nay, possibly even to truckle to <hi>France,</hi> with an absolute Resignation, under so glorious a Merit, as the Resurrection of the Popish Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars in <hi>England.</hi> This, at least, I dare boldly say, that that very Prince, who in his Abdication march towards <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham,</hi> was heard to say, <hi>He had rather be a Captain of a Troop of Light Horse under the</hi> French <hi>King, than King of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>under the Check of Parliaments, (viz.</hi> whilst those Formidable Hereticks blocks in his way to <hi>Rome</hi>) would nevertheless upon the supposition of packing such a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liment, that should have re-established his Dear <hi>Dagon</hi> Mother-Church, have hugg'd them closer than ever his Brother did his long liv'd Senate; nay, if possible, have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99474:6"/>given them Immortality, or at least Canonization for so darling a Service</p>
            <p>And here I would seriously ask, if any Man in his right Wits can believe, that ever that very <hi>Jehu-driver,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> had the least Arbitrary Design, any further than as subservient to his Popish Cause. Nay, so much the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that if fair means could have carried that Cause, undoubtedly instead of assuming any borrow'd Plumes of Power, he would have been contented to have stript half his own Royal Feathers to have purchas'd such a Blessing. And therefore why does this Argumentator play the <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefew,</hi> and start such a Chimerical Notion of an Arbitrary Power, seperate from Religion; and thus amuse the World with meer Specters and Goblins of Slavery, from a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Fear and Jealousie.</p>
            <p>But to continue my sormer Assertion, what Jem does the Crown of <hi>England</hi> want, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Indeed, were an English King a Doge of <hi>Venice,</hi> a meer Stadtholder of <hi>Holland,</hi> or any such Restricted Administrator, there were some sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of an Arbitrary Ambition of enlarging his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: But as the Crown now stands, what irregular Lust of Power can debauch any Protestant Prince, to the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the establish'd Government. 'Tis true, such an Arbitrary Sway may give him the Power of seizing any private <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard at pleasure; but what will that answer to almost half the publick Vintage of the Nation; which, whilst he Rules by Law, and Reigns in his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Hearts, he may ask and receive when ever occasion shall call for it. And besides all this, the many Royal Wrecks, the <hi>aliena pericula,</hi> would stand too visible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, to warn him from any such Encentrick Attempt: And even common King-craft it self, if no other principle of Honour, would hold him from playing that foolish Dog in the Fable.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99474:7"/>
            <p> Besides, let us take the Case even of King <hi>Charles</hi> the First: When was it that he enforced Ship-Money, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Law; but when his over-Uxorious Indulgence to his Romish Queen had render'd him suspected of Popish Designs (for still there's not even an imaginary Slavery with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Popery) which, together with his over partial Fondness of some darling Court-Favourites, had thrust him out of all Parliamentary Favour, and the least hopes of Supply that way, and consequently Necessity and crying Want only stretch'd the Prerogative in that Point. And see what a poor last shift that was, and how little worth any of his Successors Imitation (especially at the price he paid for it) when the whole Summ so extorted, was hardly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to defray the very Illuminations and Fireworks at one single Entry of a Darling Prince that carries the Hearts, and consequently the Purses of his People.</p>
            <p>Now, if Slavery cannot truly set up in <hi>England,</hi> but in conjunction with Popery, I hope this Aguish Author has no great Chills about his Heart from any Romish Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and English Shackles from that Hand; when the very Shadow of Popery can bring even Crown'd Heads to Blocks and Scaffolds: And consequently, Abdications are much a less Wonder, especially where Popery endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to set up in earnest.</p>
            <p>Nay, Popery is so far from establishing it self in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that even by our Author's own Confession, not his own terrible Slave-makers, not standing Armies can sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it. No, not an Army even modell'd for the purpose; not an Army (to use his own Words) of <hi>Debauchees, Men of no Principles, and such as make Murder their Profession,</hi> &amp;c. (for such he calls the late King's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) <hi>Page</hi> the 28th. As vile <hi>Miscreants, Hirelings,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99474:7"/>Mercenaries</hi> and <hi>Stipendaries,</hi> that at every turn he makes of Standing Armies; yet King <hi>James</hi> with all his Arts of <hi>Rome,</hi> could not even with such Tools carry his Cause. Tho' if such a mercenary Soul truly raign'd amongst the Soldiers, as this Casuist would insinuate, one would think their Fidelity to King <hi>James</hi> had been much the fairer choice, than running over to King <hi>William:</hi> For where Popery and Arbitrary Power are to be set up, a standing Army had not only more hopes of a lasting Footing, and a Soldier of Fortune to meet much larger plunder and spoil under such a Standard, (if Prey were his predominant Lust) than under a Prince and a Cause, where <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> were asserted, and consequently he could hope for no Reward but his pay.</p>
            <p>If thus stands the Inclination, even of the worst of stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Armies, I desire our Argumentator to inform us, where he will raise that standing <hi>English</hi> Army, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occasion (<hi>for such things,</hi> he tells you, <hi>may be) may come into the Field, and bid us choose these and these Men for our Representatives: Or, say Parliaments are seditious, and factious Assemblies, and therefore ought to be abolish'd: Or, encompass the Parliament-House, and threaten if they do not surrender up their Government, they will put 'em to the Sword,</hi> &amp;c. where, I say, will he find that standing Army will execute this Commission, or that bold Crown'd-head that will Command it? Here indeed he points us out a very egregious state of Slavery; and when he can ascer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the possibility of such impending Calamities over us, we'el all have as panick a fear of Chains, as himself.</p>
            <p>This Author is not contented to tell yee, the natural Bent and Inclinations of Regular Troops, so disserent from a Militia, towards enslaving us; but likewise affirms of his own knowledge, that the very Cocatrice-Egg is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready hatching. For now, he says, <hi>'tis discoursed publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99474:8"/>of</hi> 20000 <hi>Men to be maintained in Time of Peace, and if they should not gratify the Court in this modest Request, another Party may be Carest, who will Grant this, or any thing else, which is ask'd, and then they say Matters will be much worse;</hi> and, in fine, he tells you, <hi>who shall bring the Materials of Tyranny, for more expert Architects to finish the Building.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What's all this, but telling the World that the King himself is at the Head of a Conspiracy, to Enslave the Nation, (for what the Court does in that case is the Kings) what an impudent Libeller is here, (for here he speaks himself) Here's the true Cloven-foot; for, who but the Devil himself would suggest so horrid, I durst al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most say, so blasphemous a Falshood, against the divine Virtue of that Prince, that has so signalized himself our Champion and Deliverer. But the Author, by letting us know that this is <hi>familiar Discourse,</hi> gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what Company he keeps, and how glibly Treason goes down with him.</p>
            <p>I confess, in the very next Sentence, he says, <hi>We are secure from any Attempts of this kind, during the Reign of a Prince, who has rescued us from a Captivity,</hi> &amp;c. But this Cobweb Lawn is too thin; a gold Leaf to cover the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going poison: For nothing is more plain, that he means, that the King is the Head Conspirator in all this slavery; for if one Court-Faction cannot carry the Cause, he tells you, another shall be cull'd our that shall; intimating, that the Court, the Ministry, and the Hands at the Helm, shall be selected and modell'd for the purpose; and that Court-work, <hi>viz.</hi> the Choice of the Ministry, can be none but the King's; for the Project is hatch'd, the Work is going on, and proper Hands and Tools (if he durst speak plainer English) must be found.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99474:8"/>
            <p> This Gentleman exprosses all along a great Veneration for the old Commonwealth; witness his Caresses of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Sobriety, Honour, and a publick Spirit,</hi> he gives the Rump-Army, who set it up. And, indeed, he is a little driving that way himself, when in the two most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Preliminaries towards it, <hi>viz.</hi> he is poysoning the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with Jealousies, and arraigning the Faith of Kings.</p>
            <p>As to this Author's Quotations of Foreign as well as Domestick Instances of the dreadful Effects from Standing Armies, particularly in our Home-Story, he is most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently false in Matter of Fact. He tells you in one place, how small an handful of Arbitrary Troops are able to enslave this Nation; That <hi>Oliver</hi> did it with 17000: When 'tis notoriously known, that in the Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms there were near thrice the Number at once engag'd in that Quarrel.</p>
            <p>In another place, he says, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> so entirely trusted in the Love of her People, that she had no Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Forces: When, on the contrary, she was rarely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the greatest part of 40000 Regular Troops, either in her own <hi>Irish</hi> War; or in <hi>Flanders,</hi> assisting the <hi>Dutch;</hi> or the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> in <hi>France:</hi> And what was that, in effect, but in her own Service? For, in aiding the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tressed abroad, and curbing the Insults of Foreign Power, 'twas, in a manner, ballancing the Assairs of <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> and therein strengthening her self, and her People, at home.</p>
            <p>In lieu of these dangerous, Mereinary Land-Forces, he proposes the whole Bulwark and Guard of our Nation to be planted in our Naval Power: The Fleet, upon all Occasions, back'd by the Militin on Shoar, shall defend us from all Insults whatever: For, all Foreign Invasions, whilst we have a superiour Fleet to cope with them, he says, are utterly impossible.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99474:9"/>
            <p> All this while, this Author forgets what was done no longer ago than almost yesterday; We that had, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> the best Fleet in the World, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless, could not hinder the <hi>French,</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from both Landing, and Carrying off their Forces, almost at pleasure.</p>
            <p>Our Author likewise forgets that these trusty Maritime Forces are all Hirelings, very few substantial Property-Men amongst them; and therefore, by his own Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought to be suspected of as frail a Composition as a Standing Land-Army: And this I am sure, if we will suppose Corruption in our Admirals, they have it in their power, with the whole Trust of the Wooden Walls of our Kingdom, to be as pernicious to the Nation, as the most Infidel Lord Generals and Land-Armies whatever: For, what is it a Revolting Fleet cannot do? Block up our Ports; destroy our Trade, Merchants; nay, Let in a Foreign Foe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and cut the very Life-Veins of our Nation.</p>
            <p>And here again, to shew you the Veracity of the Man in our Maritime Annals, he is as wide from Truth, as in his other Quotations of History: For he tells you, the <hi>Spanish</hi> Invasion was managed with no more than 18000 Land-Forces; when, at the same time, the Prince of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> lay ready in <hi>Flanders,</hi> with near 30000 more Veterane Troops, to embark, and strike with them.</p>
            <p>But, to return to the grand Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> The Faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Accomplishing the great Work of Slavery from a Standing Army, as well as their Propensity to undertake it; for he talks as confidently of it, as of a Work almost as soon done as thought: And he accordingly tells you, <hi>That the most likely way of Restoring, King</hi> James, <hi>is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Standing Army to keep him out.</hi> And forsooth for these Reasons.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99474:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Kings Safety stands upon a Rock; whilst it depends upon the solid Foundation of the Affections of the People, which is never to be shaken, till 'tis as evident as the Sun in the Firmament, that there is a Design formed to overthrow our Laws and Liberties: But if we keep a Standing Army, all depends upon the uncertain and capricious Humours of the Souldiers, which in all Ages have produced more violent and sudden Revolutions, than ever have been known in unarmed Governments. For there is such a Chain of Dependence amongst them, that if Two or Three of the Chief Officers should be disobliged, or have Intreagues with</hi> Jacobite Mistresses, <hi>or if the King of</hi> France <hi>could once again buy his Pensioners into the Court or Army, or offer a better Market to some that are in already, we should have another Rehearsal Revolution, and the People be only idle Spectators of their own Ruine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And to give us Examples of the dangerous Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Armies, he instances, besides Foreign ones, <hi>That in our own Countrey we have but twice kept Armies in times of Peace, and both times they turned out their own Masters. The first, under</hi> Cromwel, <hi>expell'd that Parliament, under which they had fought successfully many Years: Afterwards under General</hi> Monk, <hi>they destroyed the Government they before set up, and brought back</hi> Charles <hi>the Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good Heaven! what a wretched Scarerow of Clouts is here set up, not bulky enough, when thoroughly examined, to frighten Daws.</p>
            <p>First, The <hi>Kings Safety stands unshaken till 'tis as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as the Sun, there's a Design form'd to overthrow our Laws and Liberties.</hi> Then belike, the false Pilots at the Helm must be, beyond all Shadow of Doubt, most conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuously seen to steer false, or the present Allegiance is not like to be easily stagger'd; and consequently King <hi>James</hi>'s Restoration no very casie Work. However, as his Assertion has assign'd which is the likely way for his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99474:10"/>
               <hi>viz. the keeping of a Standing Army,</hi> conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he very plainly infinuates, That the keeping a Part of the <hi>English</hi> Forces on foot (for what present Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Security whatever) is, and must be the forming such a Design against our Laws and Liberties; and that as evident as the Sun.</p>
            <p>But, not to instance the several Reasons and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities that may be urged, for some Continuance, at least, of a Part of our present Regular Military Strength, enough of it self alone to dash this whole Ridiculous <hi>Mormo</hi> out of Countenance. However, we shall try the Strength of his own <hi>Sampson</hi>-Cords of Slavery so threatned us from these dreadful Sons of Perdition, Tyranny, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidelity and Apostacy, the present dangerous Army now standing (for all these they must be, when they restore King <hi>James.</hi>)</p>
            <p>This whose Army, more or less Thousands, no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, shall be all turned inside outwards, led or misled, shall form, transform or deform, all Weathercocks, Proteuses, Camelions, or any thing, if possible, more changeable; and all, God knows, from the Caprice or Revolt of Two or Three Chief Officers, and that upon the least Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Jacobite Petticoat,</hi> or a <hi>French Louis d'Or,</hi> even to the very Restoration of King <hi>James.</hi> 'Tis true, he does well, and deals a little more ingenuously than usually with us, to tell us what manner of <hi>Jacobite Revolution</hi> this shall be, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Rehearsal One:</hi> that is as much as to say, King <hi>James</hi> shall make his Re-entry into the Chair, like the <hi>Brentford</hi> Kings, out of the Clouds; and then indeed we may be all idle Spectators of our own Ruine, at such an innocent Return of <hi>Old Jemmy viz.</hi> when he drops from the Clouds.</p>
            <p>However, to go on with the more formidable <hi>Pheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena's</hi> from this <hi>Jacobite Meteor,</hi> he instances the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99474:10"/>and Fickleness of the <hi>Standing Army</hi> under <hi>Cromwel,</hi> that expell'd their Masters; and that under <hi>Monk,</hi> that restored King <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither of those are the least Parallels in the present Case. The Revolt of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Army (though I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call them Revolters) destroy'd neither their <hi>Arts,</hi> nor <hi>Foci,</hi> neither their own, nor their Countries Religion, Rights, or invaded Liberties, as they then stood: for their turning out their <hi>Hydra-headed</hi> Masters, the <hi>Rump,</hi> for a single-headed <hi>Monster</hi> of the same Egg, was hardly to be called a <hi>Revolution.</hi> For the then Government both in Church and State stood upon the very same Anarchical, and Antimonarchical Foundation still; and indeed carried as little different a Face of Change, as whether a single <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> or he and <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> reigned together.</p>
            <p>Besides these Instances of our <hi>English</hi> standing Armies, utterly destroys his whole Argument: For, either he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, or never considers, that in both these Times, even these Hireling Armies acted in Concurrence, and moved by the same Genius, with the then Free-hold of <hi>England:</hi> The whole Torrent of the Nation, at that time, was for a Common-Wealth, which was not fully Establish'd in the then Raigning Rump, who being over and over again press'd by the <hi>Vox Populi</hi> to dissolve themselves, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a Common-wealth upon a sollid and lasting Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which they still-deny'd, their Servants, the Army (still true the publick Insterest) only dismounted them from the Saddle, into which they exalted their General <hi>Cromwel,</hi> upon his Pre-engagement and Promise, of finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Work of the <hi>Good Cause</hi> (as they call'd it) and doing the Nation that Justice, which their other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, the Rump, had refused them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwel,</hi> thus mounted, play'd much the same Game as the Rump had done; for Soveraign Power was so delicious a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99474:11"/>Morsel, that he could spare no part of it to his Friends, nothing less than all would content him; what, at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent was only given him in Trust, to be divided in a fair and equal Democracy, he made bold to engross to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</p>
            <p>This falsity of <hi>Cromwel</hi> begat some ill Blood, and a great many untoward Resentments, and, perhaps, did not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle contribute to the next Revolution; nay, <hi>Monk</hi> himself was a Malecontent, and set forth a Declaration in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that the good Cause was not fairly carried on; and the whole Nation by degrees having their Eyes open to their long Follies and Yokes, and all the Juggles of their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral upstart Lords; in short, grown weary of their own Wooden Gods, long'd for a Free Parliament, in which <hi>Monk</hi>'s Army (still Acting in consort with the whole Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold) the Army, and the Nation both agreed the great Point; and the Free-Parliament returned into their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Channel, <hi>viz.</hi> the Constitution of Monarchy, and so call'd home King <hi>Charles,</hi> still the Nation and Army con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring.</p>
            <p>Besides both these Turns of State, thus influenc'd by standing Armies, if they made any thing for his Cause, as they are the quite contrary, nevertheless have not the least Resemblance of so rapid and excentrick a Movement, as Restoring King <hi>James,</hi> a Prince of Principles so well try'd, so truly known, and so much the universal Aversion of <hi>England,</hi> that the whole <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation, Civil or Military, stands wholly against him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another Instance is fresh in every ones Memory, how King</hi> James<hi>'s Army joyn'd with the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>now our Rightful and Lawful King. And what could be expected otherwise from Men of Dissol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and Debaucked Principles, who call themselves So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldiers of Fortune, who make Murder their Profession, and enquire no further into the Justice of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99474:11"/>Cause, than how they shall be paid; who must be false, rapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and cruel in their own Defense,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Paragraph perhaps has one of the blackest Faces of any through the whole Pamphlet: For here the whole Army of King <hi>James,</hi> is araign'd as Libertines, Reprobates, Mercenaries; and Professors of nothing less than Murder, Rapine, Cruelty and Injustice, when that very Army, out of a meer Principle of Abhorrence to their Arbitrary old Master, made so general, and almost total a Caress to our Gracious approaching Deliverer the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Was there no Justice of their Cause considered, when they forsook the <hi>Popish</hi> for the <hi>Protestant</hi> Standard? nay, so considerable a Body of 'em still compose so large a Part of the present Army? Or, does not this Author play the Traveller in the Fable, and blow Hot and Cold at once, when in one Breath he calls King <hi>William, our Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Lawful King;</hi> and yet at the same time brands the whole Army that came over to his Party, and joyn'd in his glorious Work of Deliverance, as the worst of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Villians and Infidels for so doing? I wish this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing Gentleman means honestly: for I shrewdly suspect, if he's a Person of any Estate, that he's one of those Side-Friends of the Government, that paid double Taxes; one of those sober Gentlemen that swear little; for I much fear that the New Oaths had never Eloquence enough to drag into <hi>Westminster-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I cannot but look a little back to <hi>Page</hi> 6. where he gives our present King the Character of a second <hi>Moses, in reducing his People from a Captivity equal to that of the Children of</hi> Israel. <hi>A Prince, whose Life is so necessary to the Preservation of</hi> Europe, <hi>that both Protestant and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Princes have forgot their Ancient Maxims, and laid aside their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>innate Animosities, and made it their common Interest to chuse him their Patron and Protector,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99474:12"/>
            <p> Now in all this, and twenty times more Flourish of of the Pen in King <hi>William</hi>'s Panegyrick (for by the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Writer, I am afraid 'tis no more but Flourish; a soft Slur of the Pen to make his Libel pass Lash-free) I wonder how he will reconcile all his repeated <hi>Eulogies</hi> and <hi>Encomiums,</hi> even to a Transport, upon the great Work of our <hi>Mosaick</hi> Deliverer, King <hi>William,</hi> and yet at the same time so blacken the Hands that wrought in it, when nothing less than this Revolt (so much exploded by him) of King <hi>James</hi> his Army could work that Deliverance. It looks very suspiciously, that this Writer's Quarrel against them, leans the other way; not for suppressing, but for not supporting of Tyranny. He would have given them, no doubt, a much fairer Character, had they kept true to their Old Master, and their Old Cause. And that the World may be sensible how little a true Kindness this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller has for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> especially a <hi>Protestant</hi> one; we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site his Reader to consider, what dissolute Debauchees and Devils he makes King <hi>James</hi> his Army, and what Saints he makes of <hi>Olivers;</hi> which, <hi>Page</hi> 10. he tells you, <hi>must be allowed to have had as much Virtue, Sobriety and Publick Spirit, as has been known in the World amongst that sort of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here again our Author wanted a little of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering-Cap; For what more Dirt does he throw in the Face of his Argument, when he so unluckily instances this last Revolt of a Standing Army, which so entirely, (some few scatter'd Papists only excepted) join'd the Free-hold in the publick Deliverance, and though the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creatures of Popery were all, Hand and Heart, in the Performance, of what had been the common Prayers of the Nation that called over the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But supposing this Paragraph means innocently, and that from his general Aversion to <hi>Standing Armies,</hi> this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99474:12"/>Author's bold Lash was only a Random Stroke. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, when this poor Scribbler has walk'd in a long raving Dream of so many hideous Dangers from a <hi>Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and all directly levelled at the present Forces on Foot; he unfortunately wakes into Sense in the last Page of his Book, and tells us in these Words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What I have faid here against Standing Armies, I would be understood of such as are the Instruments of Tyranny, and their Countreys Ruine; and therefore I need make no Apology to our own, which was rais'd by the Consent of the Parliament in this just and necessary War; and next under God and our Great and Glorious Deliverer, have, by their Bravery and Conduct, preserved our Liberties, and the Protestant Religion through</hi> Europe.</p>
            <p>Gracious God! Is this the Character of that <hi>Standing Army,</hi> this dazling Honour and Honesty, that <hi>Pag.</hi> the 6. as beforemention'd, he tells us, The King ought to be so earnestly sollicited, right or wrong, to be immediately dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded, as of no less import than <hi>compleating our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and of no less threatning Fatality, if never so little kept up, than <hi>preying upon our very Entrails, and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to our very Constitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am afraid this Pamphleteer, by this contradictory Way of Arguing, is a little guilty of a Frailty called <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulness.</hi> And, as there are a sort of <hi>Talkers,</hi> that the Proverb says, <hi>ought to have good Memories,</hi> he gives us to understand, that as signal a Talent as he has of the first Qualification, yet it appears he is a little short in the last Capacity.</p>
            <p>If then, to summ up what has been urged, the Main Body of the Regular Forces, and those of the Militia, are much of the same Composition, and therefore no ways more or less dangerous, or less to be trusted on that Score: Next, as their Constitution and Establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99474:13"/>are so far alike, that they are equally at the King's Call, the King their Generalissimo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then, as the Great Officers in the Regular Troops are Men of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Interest in the Nation, and consequently have the same Tye, and in all Reason the same Affection for their Country's Liberty, as the Lords Lieutenants in the Militia: And also, (as the Author himself confesses,) that in a Disbanded Army, the Generality of the Soldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, upon any serviceable Call of the Trained Bands, will at least a great part of them, fall into the Militia, as Hirelings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Lastly, as from all the fore-men-mentioned Instances, 'tis manifest, Standing Forces are naturally in the Inclinations and Interests of the People; and consequently, all our Pamphleteer's Fears are Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less: Now let us examine with what Safety or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the wholy Body of our Regular Troops can be Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded, in the present State of the Kingdom, as useless to the Publick.</p>
            <p>First then, 'Tis most certain that Experience and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline makes an Army serviceable: And if the Security of the Nation requires a Martial Strength, 'tis ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously impolitick to disband the Learned, only to teach the Ignorant; and put the Government both to the Toil and Expence of making Soldiers, when we have them made to our Hands.</p>
            <p>Next, As there is not that entire Trust to be lodged in a new Reconcited Enemy, that at the first Start of a Peace, we have nothing else to do, but to turn our Swords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Plow-Shares; it being not so very many Years ago, that we have seen Peace both made, and broken again. And therefore, to speak in his own Dialect, we are not now so secure in this last Peace, but <hi>What has been, may be again.</hi> And, as no State or Government is in a true Capacity of defending it self, that has not the Power
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99474:13"/>of Offending; therefore some Cautionary Strength, in all Reason, ought to be kept on Foot upon that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count:</p>
            <p>For to speak again in his own Language, <hi>That Nation is surest to live in Peace, that is most capable of making War: And a Man that has a Sword by his side, shall have the least occasion to make use of it:</hi> All this, I say, consider'd, why must We, and We only of the whole World, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band all our Regular Troops, when our Neighbours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round us continue so considerable a Body of theirs; and as we are Embark'd in the same Common Cause, why not the same common Care of our Safety, and the same Means used to support it.</p>
            <p>I would only ask this fearful Gentleman, That if his <hi>Argument</hi> was Translated into all Languages of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, and made applicable to their own Case, (for Standing Armies enslave all Nations, as well as <hi>England</hi>) and consequently, by dint of his Eloquence, all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Forces of <hi>Europe</hi> (for the Reason holds every where alike) should be Disbanded, how many Years purchase would he give for this new Peace, as weak as he renders the present Power of <hi>France,</hi> and as fatigued as their Great Monarch may be with the Load of the late War.</p>
            <p>So much for the Safety: Now for the Honour of the Nation. <hi>First</hi> then, What Fools must the <hi>English</hi> Nation confess themselves to be, when they called over that Prince for their Deliverer, who they dare not trust with Edge Tools in his Hand, under a less Dread than of Shackles, and Rods of Iron? Next, What a Dishonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Suspicion must here be of a Prince, that has so Eminently signalized Himself a Champion of <hi>Christendom;</hi> and how must the jealous <hi>English</hi> Nation be pointed at,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99474:14"/>and hooted round the World, in their vile Fears and Jealousies, to render that very Prince a Destroying De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil at home, who has been Reverenc'd and Honour'd Abroad, pardon the Expression, almost as a Tutelary God. Good Heaven! What does this Author mean? To insinuate even but a shadow of possibility, that a Prince so Brave abroad, should be so Base at Home.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>